Kizer mss., 1921-1950 LMC 2474
Lilly Library
Kizer mss.
1921-1950
Lilly Library
Kizer, Benjamin, 1878-1978
Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931
LMC 2474
1 Box 1 standard
The Kizer mss., 1921-1950, consists of the correspondence and other materials of lawyer and diplomat Benjamin Kizer, 1878-1978.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2005
Biographical Note
Benjamin Kizer, 1878-1978, was an American attorney and diplomat. He was born on October 29, 1878 in Champaign County, Ohio, but came to Spokane, Washington with his family in 1890. He attended law school at the University of Michigan and was admitted to the bar in 1902. After his first wife Helen Bullis Kizer was killed in a riding accident in 1919, he married Mabel Ashley Kizer, 1880-1955, in 1921. Their daughter Carolyn Kizer, 1925-2014, was born on December 10, 1925. In addition to maintaining his law practice, Kizer was active in public affairs from 1944 to 1946. He served as the United National Relief and Rehabilitation Administration director in China, where he advocated for relations with China. As a result, he was charged with being a communist sympathizer. He was also active in local government in Spokane, Washington and served on many councils, including the Spokane Chamber of Commerce and the Washington State Planning Council. He died on April 8, 1978 in Spokane, Washington.
Scope and Content Note
The Correspondence series contains letters from 1920 to 1938. The China Diary series contains a draft of Kizer's manuscript regarding his experience in China. Other files in the collection include Kizer's FBI files, biographical materials, a drawing by artist and poet Vachel Lindsay, 1879-1931, photographs, clippings, inscriptions, notes, writings, and other miscellaneous items.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into I. Correspondence, II. China Diary and all other materials.
Related Material
See Kizer, C. mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Lawyers -- United States -- Biography; Diplomats -- China -- Biography; Diplomatic and consular service, Communist countries; Anti-communist movements -- United States; Kizer, Benjamin H. (Benjamin Hamilton), 1878-1978
- I. Correspondence
  - 1920-1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924 Jan-June (Box 1)
  - 1924 July-Dec (Box 1)
  - 1925 Jan-May (Box 1)
  - 1925 June-Dec (Box 1)
  - 1926-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1938 (Box 1)
  - N.D. (Box 1)
  - Extracts, 1920; 1935 (Box 1)
- II. China Diary
  - pp. 1-123 (Box 1)
  - pp. 124-250 (Box 1)
  - pp. 251-375 (Box 1)
  - pp. 376-470 (Box 1)
- Biographical materials (Box 1)
- FBI file - Benjamin Kizer (Box 1)
- Drawing by Vachel Lindsey (Box 1)
- Photographs (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1922-1939 (Box 1)
- Inscriptions, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
- Printed writings - "The Soul of the City" (Box 1)
- Printed writings, 1912-1926 (Box 1)
- Manuscript writings, 1923-1929 (Box 1)
- Notes by Kizer, 1921-1925 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1922-1927 (Box 1)